A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Office Files of Mary E. McClymont FA594
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Subject Files, 1981-2008; 2; 8.73 Cubic Feet 23 letter document boxes
  - Vera Institute -- International Police Accountability Project -- Proposal, Memoranda Re: Project Meetings, 1997-1998 (Box 15, Folder 175)
  - Vera Institute -- Working File -- Notes, Correspondence Re: Grants, 1997-2001 (Box 16, Folder 176)
  - Vera Institute -- Workshop on Police in Democratic Society, Harriman, NY -- Meeting Book, 1998 March 23-25 (Box 16, Folder 177-178)
  - West Africa -- Office Visit -- Briefing Book, 2000 February 12-19 (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Women, HIV/AIDs and the Global Fund Meeting -- Agenda, Notes, Background, 2008 January 28-29 (Box 16, Folder 180)
  - Women's Fund Social Justice Collaborative Meeting -- Meeting Book, Correspondence, 2007 November 5 (Box 16, Folder 181)
  - Women's Rights Litigation Fund -- Status Report, 1987 December 22 (Box 16, Folder 182)
  - World Bank -- Seminar on Civil Society, Foreign Aid and Sustainable Development -- Notes, Background, 1999 June 21 (Box 16, Folder 183)
  - Worldwide Governance Meeting -- Learning -- Minutes, 1996 October 18-21 (Box 16, Folder 184)
  - Worldwide International Cooperation Field Meeting, Santa Monica, CA -- Meeting Book, 2000 March 27-29 (Box 17, Folder 185-186)
  - Worldwide Philanthropy Group Meeting, Tarrytown, NY -- Meeting Book, 2000 January 5-7 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Chronological Correspondence Files, 1988-1990 (Box 20, Folder 246-248, Box 21, Folder 249)
  - Haitian Task Force (Morris), 1984-1985 (Box 21, Folder 250)
  - Seizing Opportunities: The Role of CDC in Urban Economic Development, undated (Box 21, Folder 251)
  - Forestry for Sustainable Rural Development: A Review of Ford Foundation-Supported Community Forestry Programs in Asia, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 252)
  - Lessons Learned: Proceedings of the Second Judicial Reform Roundtable held in Williamsburg, Virginia, National Center for State Courts US Agency for International Development Inter-American Development Bank., 1996 May (Box 21, Folder 253)
  - Understanding Our Rights: Review of the Public Legal Education Work of Human Rights NGOs in Kenya by Rob Watson, 1996 November (Box 22, Folder 254)
  - World Bank articles, 1998 (Box 22, Folder 255)
  - Relevant Publications for Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI), 1998 (Box 22, Folder 256-257)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) Progress Report Memo, 1997-1998 (Box 22, Folder 258)
  - Monitoring, Protecting and Promoting Worker Rights in the Global Economy, A Report Prepared for the Ford Foundation, Ian Gary, 1998-1999 (Box 22, Folder 259)
  - National and Community Service: An Analysis of Strengths, Problems, Needs, Opportunities, Prepared for the Ford Foundation by Stephanie J. Clohesy, 1999 December 11 (Box 22, Folder 260)
  - Evaluation of Emergency Set of Grants for Kosovo - Final Report, Presented to Irena Gross, Prepared by Felisa Tibbits, 2000 September (Box 23, Folder 261)
  - Summary of Discussion from Bellagio Meeting by Katharine McFate, 2000 December 15 (Box 23, Folder 262)
  - Overview of Foundation Grantmaking Trends in International Cooperation, 1999 (Box 23, Folder 263)
  - Southern Region Report from Barbara Sullivan, 2001 January 11 (Box 23, Folder 264)
  - Consultants Report in Spanish Translation and Receipt of 10,000 Dollar Fee By Regina Festa, 1999 (Box 23, Folder 265)
  - Alternative Funding for Legal advocacy in Developing Countries, Robert J. Rhudy, 2000 June (Box 23, Folder 266)
  - Building Constituencies for Social Justice: Developing a Strategic Approach, Discussion Paper Prepared for Anthony Romero, 1998 September 28 (Box 23, Folder 267)
  - Building the Latin American Human Rights Field: Increasing Institutional and Financial Sustainability for Latin American Human Rights Organizations, Joan Dassin, 1999 November 29-30 (Box 23, Folder 268)
  - Evaluation of Institutions of Higher Learning Supported by the Ford Foundation in East-Central Europe in the 1990s, and Recommendations for the Future, Prepared by Consultants Daniel Chirot and Miroslawa Grabowska, 1999 August 16 (Box 23, Folder 269)
  - Working Paper for Ford Foundation Roundtable Discussion On: What Do Women Want?, Francine Moccio, 2000 September 6 (Box 23, Folder 270)
  - U.S. Commission on Immigration Reform Reports, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 271)
  - Goals Setting and Indicator Development Workshop for Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Program Officers, 1999 February 5 (Box 23, Folder 272)
  - U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) Reports, 1997-2000 (Box 24, Folder 273)
  - Peace and Social Justice Indicators - Goal Setting and Measuring, 1996-1998 (Box 24, Folder 274)
  - John Gaventa Program Officer Memo (POM) Materials and Sessions, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 275)
  - John Gaventa, Institute of Development Services, Request for Service Agreement, 1998 (Box 24, Folder 276)
  - Evaluation Indicators - U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), 1997 September (Box 24, Folder 277)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Evaluation, 1996-1998 (Box 24, Folder 278)
  - John Gaventa - Workshop and Primer Materials, 1998-1999 (Box 24, Folder 279)
  - U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) - Strategic Plan for Haiti, Fiscal Years 1999 through 2004, 1999-2004 (Box 25, Folder 280)
  - Global Meeting, Governance and Civil Society (GCS), 2000 January (Box 25, Folder 281)
  - Hauser Center - Research Fellowship, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 282)
  - Governance and Civil Society (GCS) Articles, 1999 (Box 25, Folder 283)
  - Michael Edwards Publications on NGOs, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 284)
  - Decentralization and Democratic Local Governance Programming Handbook, Center for Democracy and Governance, Technical Publication Series, 2000 May (Box 25, Folder 285)
  - People for the American Way Foundation - Special Report: Courting Disaster: How a Scalia-Thomas Supreme Court Would Endanger Our Rights and Freedom, 2000 May 25 (Box 25, Folder 286)
  - Leadership in a Changing World, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 287)
  - Asia Regional Programming, 1999 (Box 25, Folder 288)
  - Performance Management Cycle, undated (Box 25, Folder 289)
  - Regional Grantmaking Survey and Report, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 290)
  - Senior Director Job Description, 1997-2000 (Box 25, Folder 291)
  - Individual Work Plan - Mary McClymont, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 292)
  - Reflection Memos, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 293)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Incentive Fund, 1996-1999 (Box 25, Folder 294)
  - Phyllis Chang - Program Officer Memos, 1999-2000 (Box 25, Folder 295)
  - Mary McAuley - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 25, Folder 296)
  - Tony Tillett - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 25, Folder 297)
  - Foreign Affairs March/April 1998 - The Rule of Law Revival, Thomas Carothers, Volume 77, Number Two, 1998 March-April (Box 26, Folder 298)
  - Inter-American Development Bank - Modernization of the State and Strengthening of Civil Society, undated (Box 26, Folder 299)
  - Request for Application for Global Rule of Law and Human Rights Programming, U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), 1998 (Box 26, Folder 300)
  - Center for Democracy and Governance - Alternative Dispute Resolution Practitioners Guide, 1998 March (Box 26, Folder 301)
  - Center for Democracy and Governance - User's Guide, 1997 November 1 (Box 26, Folder 302)
  - Center for Democracy and Governance - Rule of Law: Approaches to Justice Reform and What We Have Learned, A Summary of Four Papers, 1998 April (Box 26, Folder 303)
  - Strategic Assessment Framework for Democracy and Governance Programming, U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), 1998 March 6 (Box 26, Folder 304)
  - Justice and Development: The Inter-American Development Bank and Reform of the Judicial System, 1998 April (Box 26, Folder 305)
  - Searching for Democracy: The Rule of Law and Legal Reform in Latin America, Joseph R. Thome, 1998 March (Box 26, Folder 306)
  - Eastern Africa Office Mission and Program Statement, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 307)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Program Officer Memos - General, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 308)
  - Short-Form Recommendations for Grant Action (RGA), 1999 (Box 26, Folder 309)
  - Program Officer Memos Guidelines, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 310)
  - Aaron Back - Program Officer Memos, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 311)
  - Larry Cox - Program Officer Memos, 1999-2000 (Box 26, Folder 312)
  - Cristina Eguizabal - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 313)
  - Taryn Higashi - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 314)
  - Julius O. Ihonvbere - Exit Memo, 2002 (Box 27, Folder 315)
  - Alan Jenkins - Program Officer Memos, 1998-1999 (Box 27, Folder 316)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani - Program Officer Memos, 2000 (Box 27, Folder 317)
  - Chris Wang - Program Officer Memos, 1998 (Box 27, Folder 318)
  - Srilatha Batliwala - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 319)
  - Marcia Smith - Program Officer Memos, undated (Box 27, Folder 320)
  - Irena Grudzinska Gross - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 321)
  - Julius O. Ihonvbere - Program Officer Memos, 1999-2000 (Box 27, Folder 322)
  - Michael Lipsky - Program Officer Memos, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 323)
  - Other Law Program Donors/Projects, 1995-1997 (Box 27, Folder 324)
  - Judicial Reform, 1993-1999 (Box 27, Folder 325)
  - The World Bank Group Directory, 1998 (Box 27, Folder 326)
  - World Bank - Rick Messick, 1997-1999 (Box 27, Folder 327)
- Reports, 1969-2008; 3; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  This series contains reports by consultants and Ford program staff. A number of the reports were created before Ms. McClymont joined the Foundation in 1988. Topics include legal reform and human rights work in Latin America. A few reports pertain to democratization and human rights in Chile. Other reports discuss legal reform in Vietnam, citizenship in Brazil, and university law clinics in South America. This series also holds several reports on trips to Sri Lanka, Latin America, and Russia, the Czech Republic and Poland.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "The International Legal Studies Program of the Ford Foundation" by Murray L. Schwartz, 1969 December (Box 17, Folder 188)
  - "Legal Education" by Arthur von Mehren, 1970 January 17 (Box 17, Folder 189)
  - "Public Interest Law and Human Rights in Brazil" by David Trubek, 1977 May 30 (Box 17, Folder 190)
  - "Law and Social Justice: Brazil" by David Trubek, 1978 December (Box 17, Folder 191)
  - "Work with the South African Legal Resources Centre" by George Cooper, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 192)
  - "Survey of the Current Status of National Women's Rights Organizations" by Marjorie Fine Knowles, 1983 October 26 (Box 17, Folder 193)
  - "Expanding Justice: Review of the Ford Foundation Legal Services Program" by Dorothy J. Samuels, 1984 January (Box 17, Folder 194)
  - "Status Report on Foundation Work in Dispute Resolution", 1985 December (Box 17, Folder 195)
  - "Encouraging Stability, Peace and Justice in the International Order" by Joseph S. Nye, Jr., I.M. Destler, I.G. Patel and Jose Zalaquett, 1987 June (Box 17, Folder 196)
  - "Pluralism and Diversity" by Nathan I. Huggins, Mary Schmidt Campbell, Elaine R. Jones and Jose Zalaquett, 1987 June (Box 17, Folder 197)
  - "Evaluation of the Chilean Commission for Human Rights and the Vicarate of Solidarity" by Margaret E. Crahan, 1986 October (Box 18, Folder 198)
  - "Legal Reform in the USSR and Possibilities for Western Help" by Valery Chalidze, 1989 March 1 (Box 18, Folder 199)
  - "Report to the Ford Foundation on Legal Services Support Centers" by Leah Wortham and Robert Dinerstein, 1989 November (Box 18, Folder 200)
  - "Making Rights Real: Human Rights in Latin America and the Caribbean" by Scott Busby, 1989 December (Box 18, Folder 201)
  - "Sugerencias Para el Trabajo de Organizaciones no Gubernamentales de Derechos Humanos en Peru y Argentina" by Lucenciada Patricia Tappata de Valdez, 1989 December 31 (Box 18, Folder 202)
  - "Human Rights in South America" by Juan E. Mendez, 1990 January 1 (Box 18, Folder 203)
  - "Sri Lanka Trip Report" by R. Sudarshan, 1990 February 20 (Box 18, Folder 204)
  - "Chile: Human Rights in Transition" by Cynthia Brown, 1990 September 1 (Box 18, Folder 205)
  - "Towards Justice: Foundation Programs in Human Rights and Social Justice and Governance and Public Policy in the Philippines" by Terrence George, 1991 February 20 (Box 18, Folder 206)
  - "Problems of Citizenship in Brazil" by James Holston, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 207)
  - "Trip to Latin America" (Colombia, Peru and Chile) by Mary McClymont, 1992 January 9 (Box 18, Folder 208)
  - "The Ford Foundation and International Security" by Catherine McArdle Kelleher and Robert O'Neill, 1992 April (Box 18, Folder 209)
  - "Legal Education and Research and Law Reform in Vietnam" by Mark Sidel, 1992 April (Box 18, Folder 210)
  - "The Challenge for the Decade of the '90s: A Survey of Trends and Issues Related to Refugees, Asylees, Migrants and the Internally Displaced" by Guy Goodwin-Gill, Gil Loescher and Julia Taft, 1992 May (Box 18, Folder 211)
  - "Ford Foundation Rights and Social Justice Program Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa" (rapporteur notes), 1993 May 23-27 (Box 18, Folder 212)
  - "Report on the Status of University Law Clinics in South Africa" by M. Shanara Gilbert, 1993 November 15 (Box 18, Folder 213)
  - "Promoting Rights and Social Justice: A Historical Survey of Ford Foundation Programs for African American and Latino Communities" by Sarita Ahuja, 1994 November (Box 18, Folder 214)
  - "Trip to Russia, Czech Republic and Poland" by Mary McClymont, 1994 November 22 (Box 18, Folder 215)
  - "The Ford Foundation's International Human Rights Program: A History and an Agenda" by Margo Picken, 1995 January 30 (Box 18, Folder 216)
  - "Municipal Government and Political Participation in Chile" by Gary Bland, 1995 February 28 (Box 18, Folder 217)
  - "Fiscalizacin y Control Ciudadanos en un Rgimen Poltico Democrtico: Los Casos de Colombia, Chile, Argentina y Per" by Hugo Frhling, circa 1996 (Box 18, Folder 218)
  - "Una Vez Ms la Miseria: Es Chile un Pas Sustenable?" by Marcel Claude, 1996 (Box 18, Folder 219)
  - "Polticas Ambientales en Chile, 1990-1995" by Laura Mullahy, 1996 March (Box 18, Folder 220)
  - "From Political Liberalization to Democratization" by Jonathan N. Moyo, 1996 April 30 (Box 18, Folder 221)
  - Beyond Boundaries (Toronto: University of Toronto, 1997) by Navnita Chadha Behera, Paul M. Evans and Gowher Rizvi (Box 19, Folder 222)
  - "History of the Ford Foundation's Work on Police Issues" by Michelle Dash, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 223)
  - "Reporte para la Fundacin Ford" (Legal Clinics and Public Interest Law Report) by Martin Federico Bohmer, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 224)
  - "Round Table on Law and Justice in Brazil" by David Trubek, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 225)
  - "A Measure of Choice: A Strategic Review of the Madaripur Legal Aid Association's Current Impact and Possible Future Directions" by Stephen Golub, 1997 January (Box 19, Folder 226)
  - "Adapting the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative to Latin America" by Ramn Borges Mndez, 1997 April 4 (Box 19, Folder 227)
  - "Review of the Ford Foundation Human Rights and Social Justice Program in the Middle East and North Africa" by Emma Playfair, 1997 May (Box 19, Folder 228)
  - "Decentralization, Local Governance and Democracy in Chile", 1997 June 16 (Box 19, Folder 229)
  - "Public Interest Actions in the Andean Region and Southern Cone Region", 1997 June 15 (Box 19, Folder 230)
  - "Symposium on Public Interest Law in Eastern Europe and Russia" (report) by Public Interest Law Initiative, 1997 June 29-July 8 (Box 19, Folder 231)
  - "The Environment, Sustainable Development and Democratization in Chile", 1997 July 14 (Box 19, Folder 232)
  - "Nongovernmental Organizations in Chile", 1997 July 23 (Box 19, Folder 233)
  - "Assessment of Public Interest Law Initiative (PILI) in Bangladesh" by Stephen Golub, 1997 September 22 (Box 19, Folder 234)
  - "A Review of the Ford Foundation's Work Related to Hispanics in the U.S." by Evelyn Dvila, Jos Roberto Jurez, Jr. and Edwin Melndez, 1997 November (Box 19, Folder 235)
  - "Juridical Services as a Strategy for Combating Racism" by Dora Luca de Lima Bertulio, 1998 February (Box 19, Folder 236)
  - "Reflections on Encounter Groups of Jews and Palestinians from Israel" by Haggith Gor Ziv and Rela Mazali, 1998 April (Box 19, Folder 237)
  - "The Innovations in Government Programs" by Judith Tendler, 1998 April 14 (Box 19, Folder 238)
  - "Gay and Lesbian Concerns: Past, Current and Future Programming by the Ford Foundation" by Priscilla Hayner, 1998 July 29 (Box 19, Folder 239)
  - "Evaluation of Institutions of Higher Learning Supported by the Ford Foundation in East-Central Europe in the 1990s and Recommendations for the Future" by Daniel Chirol and Miroslawa Grabowska, 1999 August 16 (Box 19, Folder 240)
  - "Building the Latin American Human Rights Field" by Dr. Joan Dassin, 1999 September 24 (Box 19, Folder 241)
  - "Ford Foundation Peace and Social Justice Program Worldwide Meeting, Krakow, Poland, Jun 4-9, 2000: Rapporteur's Report", 2000 July 5 (Box 19, Folder 242)
  - "A Review of UN Reform-Related Projects Supported by the Ford Foundation, 1985-1996" by Edward C. Luck, 2001 May 25 (Box 19, Folder 243)
  - "Towards Enhanced Work on Conflict" by Teresa Whitfield, 2001 July 2 (Box 19, Folder 244)
  - "Deepening Democracy Worldwide" by Christopher Reardon, 2008 January 7 (Box 19, Folder 245)